Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Social Sciences Division Projects, 2014-2021
  - Social Research and Public Policy
    - Kochar, Nandini. A Critical Reflection on Ethnography, Documentary and Ethnographic Film: Power, Positionality and Reflexivity, 2021; 2021-0216 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0216)
      In this paper, I reflect on the process of developing an ethnographic documentary, the ethical dilemmas that came with it, and the larger questions of power, positionality and agency that it gave rise to. This paper also centers emotions as a means of tracing my internal journey as a student filmmaker and ethnographer, and in doing so, hopes to contribute to an expanding dialogue about the importance of ethical reckoning and reflexivity in ethnographic and documentary practices. This paper is part of a joint-capstone project in Film and New Media (Practice) and Social Research and Public Policy.
      Author provided keywords: documentary; ethnography; ethics; self-reflexivity; positionality; power; gaze
    - Morikawa, Misa. Gender Inequality in University Attainment, Employment, and Earnings in Japan: A Comparison with the United States, 2021; 2021-0206 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0206)
      Despite its high levels of development, Japan is yet to achieve gender equality, and often scores much lower in measures of gender equality than countries with similar levels of development. This paper tackles the question: is Japan exceptional in its gender inequality, especially in its university attainment, employment, and wage? We conduct a comparative analysis on the US and Japan through regression analyses on the data from Luxembourg Income Study. Our analyses reveal that the gender gap in university attainment is reversed in both countries, with higher female university attainment than their male counterparts, and the US widened the female superiority slightly more quickly than Japan. Analyses on employment shows that, contrary to past literature, Japan has a smaller gender gap than the US, with US widening the gender gap in recent cohort while Japan diminishes the gap. The gender wage gap is larger in Japan than the US and its exceptionalism has decreased in the recent cohort.
      Author provided keywords: Gender Inequality, Gender Wage Gap, Japan
    - Mussa, Nejat. The Psychosocial Impacts of Infertility and Mechanisms Used by Ethiopian Women to Cope with them: A Qualitative Study, 2021; 2021-0215 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0215)
      Despite the huge prevalence of infertility in the African continent, the experiences of African women with infertility remains understudied. Thus, research exploring the consequences of infertility and the coping mechanisms used by women to navigate through this consequence is crucial in the fields of reproductive and mental public health. To this end, this qualitative study investigated the mechanisms used by 10 infertile Ethiopian women to cope with mental consequences of infertility- stress and anxiety. Using data from a single round of in-depth semistructured interviews with women getting treated at AlHikmah Fertility Center, a combination of emotion and problem-focused coping strategies are identified. Emotion-based coping mechanisms such as praying for strength, meditation and suppressing were used to manage emotions and assert control over the situation. Problem-focused coping mechanisms were employed to look for solutions through learning about infertility and seeking instrumental social support. The findings of this study may assist public health professionals and policymakers to design and implement interventions that emphasize holistic health care provision in fertility centers. Through holistic healthcare, access to better mental health services and enhanced awareness about infertility can be possible. This not only reduces the mental impact of infertility but also improves the patients' understanding of it.
      Author provided keywords: Infertility treatment, coping mechanisms, Anxiety management
    - Parrth, Pranaav. The Role of Trust as a Determinant of Fundraising Success in Nascent Venture Capital Ecosystems: The Case of the G.C.C., 2021; 2021-0208 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0208)
      This paper seeks to investigate the role of trust as a determinant of fundraising success in nascent venture capital ecosystems. Utilising interviews with both VC managers as well as investors (LPs), the paper seeks to understand different factors and strategies deployed by stakeholders that lead to establishment trust and fundraising success. Venture ecosystems such as the G.C.C. are fairly nascent compared to mature VC ecosystems such as the United States. Given the dearth of financial returns data on VC funds, this paper seeks to investigate the factors that potential investors (LPs) prioritise in the absence of returns data in order to assess the trustworthiness of VCs and how these factors potentially affect their investment decisions. The paper also examines factors that VC managers prioritise while pitching to potential LPs. Utilising interviews from both investors as well as managers gives the paper a holistic perspective in understanding the trust relations between the two stakeholders. This paper offers insights for not just venture practitioners but also entrepreneurs and other observers of venture ecosystems in emerging markets.
      Author provided keywords: Trust, Venture Capital
    - Reggy-Beane, Otelo. Expanding Opportunity in Low-Income Neighborhoods: Effect of the Low-Income Housing Tax Credit on Neighborhood Gentrification, 1990 to 2010, 2021; 2021-0207 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0207)
      There is growing concern that subsidized housing only concentrates poverty in low-income neighborhoods. This paper analyzes the underexplored causal effect of the Low-Income Housing Tax Credit (LIHTC), the largest subsidized housing provider in the U.S., on gentrification in low-income urban neighborhoods from 1990 to 2010. Using propensity score matching, the paper finds that the average LIHTC-funded neighborhood is substantially more likely to gentrify than non-LIHTC-funded neighborhoods and that LIHTC-funded development likely contributes directly to this effect. These findings suggest that LIHTC-funded development, through the creation of mixed-income housing, attracts higher-income, college-educated residents, whose heightened presence could be conducive to a proliferation of neighborhood amenities and an increased likelihood of low-income residents attending and completing college. In other words, subsidized housing development could be transforming low-income neighborhoods from within into spaces of opportunity. Nevertheless, the paper considers the classed and racialized nature of gentrification that governs low-income residents' access to opportunity in their revitalized neighborhoods. Framing LIHTC-funded development as state-supported gentrification, the paper discusses what these findings mean for the future of subsidized housing policy and recommends policies to guide federal policymakers in ensuring subsidized housing development upholds equity and inclusion.
      Author provided keywords: Low-Income Housing Tax Credit, gentrification, affordable housing
    - Sheikh, Maira. Hiding among the "Hidden Population": The Teachers and School Leaders of the Pakistani Schools in the UAE, 2021; 2021-0213 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0213)
      The school staff (teachers and school leaders) are considered critical actors in the quality of our educational systems. Pakistani schools in the UAE are an example of schools with a primarily dominant immigrant student body and relatively low resources which rely heavily on the 'hard work' of its educators. However, at the same time, very little efforts are made to understand the complex realities of the circumstances in which they work. Therefore, through in-depth semi-structured interviews, this study uses the narratives and experiences of teachers and school leaders to explore the landscape for the school staff in the Pakistani schools of the UAE. In this paper, I specifically discuss how the scope conditions of the school imposes 'extra responsibilities' to be exhibited by teachers and school administrators. I present these extra responsibilities as an overlap between responsibilities that are formally designated to them and those that emerge informally. Through this paper, I also seek to disseminate the findings of the research to relevant organisations and authorities as an attempt to initiate meaningful discourse and support structural improvements
      Author provided keywords: Pakistani Schools, Low-resourced, Formal and Informal Roles, Extra-Responsibilities, Structural Improvements
    - Sullivan, Caroline. Vote by Mail Policy Adoption in the U.S.: A Shift to Partisan Calculus, 2021; 2021-0198 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0198)
      This paper presents an analytical narrative of vote by mail policy changes in Iowa and Indiana and utilizes a dataset to contextualize those changes across all 50 states. Most fundamentally, this paper aims to answer why Iowa expanded vote by mail in the general election in response to the pandemic while Indiana did not. In both states, there was a possibility for change: Covid-19 widened the policy window for greater access and both states took steps to do so. However, in a key time period between the primary and general elections, the influence of national narratives driven by elites changed the rules of the game. No longer could vote by mail follow its historically nonpartisan logic; instead, it fell into the same calculus of partisan electoral advantage that dictates the adoption of most other voting rules. There is a strikingly similar process of politicization in both states; differences in outcomes arise from the policy feedback of a longstanding policy in Iowa and the barriers and openings created by political institutions in both states. This paper adds to the increasingly relevant literature on voting rights in the United States and fills a gap with its focus on vote by mail.
      Author provided keywords: voting rights, state policy adoption, vote by mail
    - Tymoshenko, Julia. How the East and West Report: A Qualitative Study Examining the Relationship Between Peer Monitoring Tendencies and Culture, 2021; 2021-0202 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0202)
      Large international companies play a major role in the globalization, specifically, by facilitating the migration of skilled labor. As a result of operating in and hiring from different markets, these international companies have a diverse workforce that is formed by people with various cultural and ethnic backgrounds who come together to work towards shared company goals. From an organizational and employee perspective, it is important to understand how people monitor each other's performance. Can peer monitoring tendencies of individuals be driven by their cultural origins and values? This qualitative study explores this question in the context of Western offices of large international technology companies. Twenty interviews with a situational vignette reveal differences in peer monitoring tendencies between people from Western and Eastern cultures: when Eastern employees notice a slacker on their team, it takes them longer to report the problem to the manager compared to their Western counterparts. The study also reveals that men tend to choose their peer monitoring mechanisms based on different contextual conditions while women tend to have an unconditional approach. These findings suggest that cultural and gender differences can have implications on individual careers, team dynamics and performance monitoring in organizations.
      Author provided keywords: Peer, reporting, monitoring, employee, manager, organization, collectivism, individualism, culture
    - Vallejo, Claudia Gabriela Neumann. The "Other Way" of Doing Leadership: Lessons from Women Leaders in Paraguayan Precarious Settlements, 2021; 2021-0199 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0199)
      Contemporary Paraguayan female academics and activists have made significant efforts to vindicate the myriad contributions of Paraguayan women throughout the country's history. They emphasize the role of las disconformes, women who worked for and dreamed of an "other way" of doing politics in a country that has been continuously led by men. In a machista culture with an ongoing lack of female presence in high leadership positions, it is interesting to see that hundreds of women living in precarious settlements are occupying the higher leadership positions available in their communities. In addition, these women are effectively achieving community organization and improvement. This research is a qualitative study about women leaders in precarious settlements from the Metropolitan Area of Asuncion, Paraguay. The main goal of this study is to understand how the particular characteristics of women leaders in precarious Paraguayan settlements are enhancing community organization and improvement. Being a woman, especially a woman living in a precarious settlement, has equipped them with "what it takes" to organize their communities to achieve essential gains. The stories of these women leaders can help us better understand how far we can go as a society if we start giving place to women and their "other way" of doing leadership.
      Author provided keywords: Leadership, Paraguay, Precarious Settlements, Feminism, Women Leaders, Land inequality
    - Xu, Yao. Anti-Chinese Sentiment in the United States amid the COVID-19 Pandemic, 2021; 2021-0209 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0209)
      Anti-Asian sentiment and hate crimes in the United States spiked during the COVID-19 pandemic, raising awareness and concerns of discrimination and racism towards this group of "perpetual foreigners" and foregrounding policy-relevant discussions. Individuals with connections to China, the first country that reported clusters of COVID-19 cases, are likely to be especially affected. In this paper, we investigate unequal treatment towards Chinese-born individuals living in the United States as compared to their U.S.-born counterparts using an experimental approach, more specifically with the give-or-take dictator game. Relying on a nationally representative sample and two survey waves fielded in May and October 2020, the paper contributes to the existing literature by examining behavioral evidence of unequal treatment and the associations between various COVID-19 related threats and mistreatment. We find evidence of Chinese alters receiving worse treatment in the first but not the second wave of data collection. Moreover, the investigations on self-reported and community-level exposure to health-related, economic, and symbolic threats revealed the impact of political identification on the exacerbated unequal treatment of Chinese-born U.S. residents.
      Author provided keywords: Anti-Chinese sentiment, COVID-19, dictator game, political identification
- Other Capstone Documentation, [2016-2020]; 2014-2022
  Other Capstone Documentation includes acquired audio and video from Divisional Capstone Festivals, student presentations about their projects, awards documentation, and other materials that are about Capstones but are not part of the projects themselves. Includes digital photos, videos, and slides. This series is minimally processed and preserved in its original transferred or acquired arrangement.
  - Arts & Humanities Division Capstone Festivals Archive, 2014, 2016-2022; 2 Terabytes (Box Electronic Records, E-records AD-MC-004)
    Includes audiovisual materials (photos, posters, films, filmed performances) associated with Arts and Humanities Division student Capstone Projects.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    These files were either created by AV Library team members, or acquired from the Division.
  - Engineering Division Capstone Festivals Archive, 2016-2022; 20.45 Gigabytes (Box Electronic Records, E-records AD-MC-004)
    Includes photos, videos, presentation videos, and Capstone booklets.
    Transferred by the Engineering Division Operations Manager (Office of the Dean)
  - Science Division Capstone Festivals Archive, 2020-2022 (Box Electronic Records, E-records AD-MC-004)
    Includes filmed presentations and other accompanying materials by students who participated in the Science Division Capstone Festivals, 2020-present.
  - Social Sciences Capstone Festivals and Awards Archive, 2015-2022; 3.98 Gigabytes 130 electronic files (Box Electronic Records, E-records AD-MC-004)